Guide to the Edwin Lee Jones Papers, 1908-1981 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Edwin Lee Jones papers 1908-1981 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jones, Edwin Lee
4.4 Linear Feet 3,268 Items
Official observer of the atomic bomb test in Bikini, Marshall Islands, July 1, 1946. Former secretary-general, general manager, president, and chairman of the board of J. A. Jones Construction Co. of Charlotte, N.C.
Consists of correspondence, addresses and writings, legal and financial papers, clippings, printed materials, photographs, memorabilia, diaries, and scrapbooks related to Edwin Lee Jones and members of his family, including his father, daughter, son, wife, and brothers. Topics include the activities of the J. A. Jones Construction Company, Duke University student life, the Methodist Church, the Marshall Islands atom bomb tests, ship-building in WWII, and the military career of Edwin's son in the Marine Corps on Parris Island, SC, and in other schools in the South. Although most of the pictures are of the Jones family, there are also photographs relating to an awards ceremony held in honor of J. A. Jones Construction Co.'s prodigious production of "liberty ships" during WWII. The writings and addresses and printed materials document Jones's activities with various religious and philanthropic organizations, while the volumes include a travel journal, as well as several scrapbooks and ledgers recording Jones's personal expenditures from 1918 to 1959. Numerous legal and financial papers pertain to the settling of Jones's estate following his death in 1971. Addition includes letters (5 items; dated 1946) written by Jones describing the preparations for the atomic bomb test and the effects of the explosions on Bikini and Kwajalein atolls.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edwin Lee Jones Papers were received from 1970-1992 by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Collection Overview
Consists of correspondence, addresses and writings, legal and financial papers, clippings, printed materials, photographs, memorabilia, scrapbooks, and diaries pertaining to Edwin Lee Jones and his family. Many letters were written by Jones's daughter Louise as a student at Duke University, the Three Arts Club, and a New York City fashion school, and also as the wife of U.S. Army officer Franklin Brown in Oak Ridge, Tenn. There are even more letters from Jones's son Edwin as a youth at Camp Carolina in Brevard N.C., as a student at McCallie Prep School in Chattanooga, Tenn., at West Point, and at Duke University. His letters also document his military career as a Marine Corps recruit at Parris Island, S.C., an officer candidate in Quantico, Va, and an officer in the Pacific during WWII, including duty in Japan. These letters often reflect his stuggle to maintain a Christian lifestyle.
Other correspondents include Jones's father, J. A. Jones; his brothers, James A. Jones and Raymond A. Jones, both of whom were involved in the family business; his wife Annabel; and others, especially Dilworth M.E. Church of Charlotte. Jones's return correspondence describes his involvement in the Methodist Church, and his activities on behalf of the J. A. Jones Construction Co., much of which involved U.S. military bases and projects in Central and South America. Also present are Jones's descriptive letters to his wife Annabel concerning preparations for, as well as consequences of, the atom bomb test of 1946 near Bikini Atoll in the South Pacific. Additional materials concerning the test can be found among the miscellaneous papers and pictures.
Although most of the pictures in the Photographs Series are of the Jones family, there are also pictures relating to an awards ceremony held in honor of J. A. Jones Construction Co.'s prodigious production of "liberty ships" during WWII.
The writings and addresses and printed materials document Jones's activities with various religious and philanthropic organizations, while the volumes include a travel journal, as well as several scrapbooks and ledgers recording Jones's personal expenditures from 1918 to 1959. Numerous legal and financial papers pertain to the settling of Jones's estate following his death in 1971.
Addition includes letters (5 items; dated 1946) written by Jones describing the preparations for the atomic bomb test and the effects of the explosions on Bikini and Kwajalein atolls.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University
J. A. Jones Construction
McCallie School (Chattanooga, Tenn.)
Parris Island (S.C.)
United States. Marine Corps
United States Military Academy
Atomic bomb -- Blast effect
College students -- United States
Nuclear weapons -- Testing
Operation Crossroads, Marshall Islands, 1946
Methodist Church -- North Carolina
World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Ocean
Bikini Atoll (Marshall Islands)
Kwajalein Atoll (Marshall Islands)
Marine Corps Base Quantico (Va.)
Contents of Collection
- Biographical Information Series, (1 box)
  - Information Folder (Box 1)
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
    - Annabel Lambeth Jones (Box 1)
    - Edwin Lee Jones, 1891-1971 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1908-1971 and undated, (5 boxes)
  - 1908-1934 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1938 (Box 3)
  - 1939-1941 (Box 4)
  - 1942-1945 (Box 5)
  - 1946-1971 and undated (Box 6)
- Addresses and Writings Series, (1 box)
  - Addresses and writings (Box 7)
- Financial Papers Series, (1 box)
  - Financial Papers (Box 7)
- Miscellany Series, (1 box)
  - Misc. (Box 8)
- Clippings Series, (2 boxes)
  - Clippings (Box 8-9)
- Printed Material Series, (2 boxes)
  - Various Printed materials (Box 9-10)
- Pictures Series, (2 boxes)
  - Pictures (Box 11-12)
- Memorabilia Series, (1 box)
  - Memorabilia (Box 12)
- Volumes Series, (2 boxes)
  - Volumes (Box 13-14)
- Addition, (1 box)
  - Accession 1989 June 16 (Box 1)
- Additional Materials
  - Papers, 1946 (Folder 1)
- Oversize Materials
  Consists of black and white photographs; diplomas; nautical chart of Marshall Islands; pennant; and various newspapers including Jones Journal and Trinity Chronicle
  - Oversize Items (Opaperfolder OF1)